<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
   <title>Up the duff with diabetes</title>
   <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="./" />
   <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="./atom.xml" />
   <id>tag:type1mum.net,2007://1</id>
   <updated>2007-06-09T12:04:42Z</updated>
   <subtitle>One woman&apos;s journey into the labyrinth...</subtitle>
   <generator uri="http://www.sixapart.com/movabletype/">Movable Type 3.34</generator>

<entry>
   <title>27 weeks! and all is well...</title>
   <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="./27_weeks_and_all_is_well.html" />
   <id>tag:type1mum.net,2005://1.223</id>
   
   <published>2005-10-19T08:54:01Z</published>
   <updated>2007-04-15T02:51:38Z</updated>
   
   <summary>Finally an update! Have been meaning to write for so long again but time just runs away at the moment, with every spare moment taken up by the things on my To Do Before Bub 2 List... fence will be...</summary>
   <author>
      <name>anon</name>
      
   </author>
         <category term="2nd Pregnancy" scheme="http://www.sixapart.com/ns/types#category" />
   
   
   <content type="html" xml:lang="en" xml:base="./">
      Finally an update! Have been meaning to write for so long again but time just runs away at the moment, with every spare moment taken up by the things on my To Do Before Bub 2 List...

fence will be up tomorrow...
room painted soon...
car has been serviced, now has air con...
new bolt in car for baby capsule...
garage cleared out to make room for cool play space and occasionally the car...

But to sum up, besides the tiredness at the end of the day I feel fantastic. I LOVE the second trimester. I feel as though my sugar levels have been more erratic with this pregnancy but my HbA1C is still at 5.9 which I&apos;m really happy about. So far my ultrasound scans look good. Bub&apos;s due date has been set at 17th January 2006 and he is measuring perfectly for these dates. Blood pressure still normal. Protein in the urine less than it was at this time last pregnancy. Albumin levels higher (which is a good thing). My endocrinologist says not to place too much stock in these readings as each pregnancy is different, but basically &apos;So far so good&apos;. 

My ob is talking about 37-38 weeks as being their goal for me and although I think it&apos;s ambitious, given how oedemic I was just before 37 weeks last time, I must admit this makes me happy. It will be interesting to see what my old ob says when I swap back to her
      
   </content>
</entry>
<entry>
   <title>32 weeks - all good but sore feet!</title>
   <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="./32_weeks_all_good_but_sore_fee.html" />
   <id>tag:type1mum.net,2005://1.224</id>
   
   <published>2005-11-21T08:32:27Z</published>
   <updated>2007-04-15T02:51:38Z</updated>
   
   <summary>Wow - five weeks since my last post. This is shocking but some indication of how busy life with a toddler is when you&apos;re pregnant with diabetes and trying to get heaps done! From a medical point of view things...</summary>
   <author>
      <name>anon</name>
      
   </author>
         <category term="2nd Pregnancy" scheme="http://www.sixapart.com/ns/types#category" />
   
   
   <content type="html" xml:lang="en" xml:base="./">
      Wow - five weeks since my last post. This is shocking but some indication of how busy life with a toddler is when you&apos;re pregnant with diabetes and trying to get heaps done!

From a medical point of view things are going really well. I&apos;m 32 weeks tomorrow. Checking with my old ob&apos;s records and my endocrinologist&apos;s records I already had moderate oedema by this stage with the last pregnancy and I have none now. Yay!! This time last pregnancy I had around 2g of protein a day in my urine and this time I have 0.62g. I also have slightly higher serum albumin, which is a good thing too,  at the moment. 

This has pretty much flabbergasted me as I had assumed that my pregnancy, oedema and pre-eclampsia wise, would follow pretty much the same timeframe as with my last pregnancy and this bub would be born at 35, 36 weeks at the latest. My daughter was born at just before 37 weeks, which I reckoned was probably too late, resulting in my caesarean scar opening due to fluid leaking out (massive oedema) and the vision and language disturbances I experienced  for days after the birth that I feel were almost certainly due to cerebral oedema (scary). I had also put on 27 kg by the time my daughter was born. This time, so far, I have put on 8kg. So fingers crossed

The irony is that me doing so well means bub is (hopefully!) going to arrive right at peak public holiday time over Christmas.... The docs reckon a delivery between 37 and 38 weeks is best and have penned me in for a caesarean when I am 37 weeks and 1 day along. Originally I was chuffed at this idea as it meant I&apos;d get further along in the pregnancy than I ever expected to, but now I&apos;m having thoughts like, &apos;What if I&apos;m going really well? Will bub&apos;s lungs be mature enough? Should we pluck bub out at this pre-ordained time or let him stay in a bit longer?&apos;.

The whole thing is complicated by a number of factors. Firstly I reckon my official due date of 17.1.06 is ambitious ie bub could not be due one single day earlier. I kept a &apos;chart&apos; for the first time ever the month we conceived and according to my records the date of 17.1.06  means the pregnancy must have begun within a few hours of us having sex! (It was the first time we&apos;d had sex in ten days.) I remember the night so clearly because we&apos;d gone out for dinner that night with friends, something we very rarely do these days, and they had told us they were five weeks pregnant and said, &apos;here&apos;s some inspiration for you&apos;! I had also noticed mucous (signalling ovulation) that morning, something I hadn&apos;t noticed much since having my daughter and breastfeeding (which I had only given up the month before). So the due date surely is probaby a day or two later than the 17th. Have been trying to ask doctors about this but I think they all think I&apos;m being ridiculously pedantic. Am I making mountains out of molehills? Maybe ... but I&apos;d love bub to stay in as long as is healthiest for the two of us and having an accurate estimate of the due date seems like part of that.

Problem 2. My ob gets back from overseas on the Thursday before my c-section is booked. I see her at 1pm on the Friday. Then the whole world finishes work for the Christmas holidays. I am due to have the c-section at 7am the following Wednesday (28 December) ie first working day after Christmas public holidays! So if my ob wants to change anything eg dates, people, the giving of steroids for lung maturity etc... it doesn&apos;t give her (or me) much time. Also, rescheduling would probably mean rescheduling for dead on 38 weeks, after the next public holidays for New Years and I&apos;d be nervous about doing this unless I was able to be monitored closely over the 37-38 week period.

Anyhow, I am raving on, very very tired so I hope some of this is making sense.

Other factors are that my endo goes on leave on 1st January and my old ob who I hope might be able to assist at the caesar also goes on leave on the 1st. Hmmm...

My brain is fading so I should go, but remind me to write about stem cells... yet more fun and games...

(tee hee, when I read this more than a year later I realise I titled it ... sore feet and then went on to mention nothing about sore feet! At some point during both pregnancies, and also after bub was born, I experienced pain in the arches of my feet (no doubt because of the extra weight of either being pregnant or carrying bub and possibly the changes to the connective tissue during pregnancy). I found great relief for this by using gel arch supports (available from the chemist) inside my shoes and so far, it&apos;s only ever been very temporary.)
      
   </content>
</entry>
<entry>
   <title>Cord Blood Stem Cell Drama</title>
   <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="./cord_blood_stem_cell_drama.html" />
   <id>tag:type1mum.net,2005://1.225</id>
   
   <published>2005-11-23T09:34:37Z</published>
   <updated>2007-04-15T02:51:38Z</updated>
   
   <summary>I&apos;d had my daughter&apos;s cord blood privately collected and stored two years ago so assumed even though I had changed obstetricians that it would be pretty straightforward to have this done again. After all, I was booked in to the...</summary>
   <author>
      <name>anon</name>
      
   </author>
         <category term="2nd Pregnancy" scheme="http://www.sixapart.com/ns/types#category" />
   
   
   <content type="html" xml:lang="en" xml:base="./">
      I&apos;d had my daughter&apos;s cord blood privately collected and stored two years ago so assumed even though I had changed obstetricians that it would be pretty straightforward to have this done again. After all, I was booked in to the same hospital.

Not so...

After over a month of agonising, phone calls and research, I&apos;ve come to the conclusion that different obstetricians have different attitudes towards private cord blood storage as well as different levels of experience with cord blood collection. It seems that some obstetricians refuse to collect it for private storage, others do so without supporting it and others do so quite willingly.

My obstetrician informed me when I first ran the idea by her that the hospital I was booked into had changed policy, meaning that midwives could no longer assist with private cord blood collections at the birth as the hospital was scared of being sued for anything going wrong. They also refused to let external midwives (used by some private cord blood storage companies) in to collect the blood. She said that if I had a caesarean (which was highly likely) it would probably take the obstetrician involved around 30 minutes to get back  to the placenta (which would have been set aside in a dish)  to collect the cord blood as it would take this long to finish the surgery and finish stitching me up etc. By 30 minutes she said there was a high likelihood that the cord blood would have congealed. It would also have a higher incidence of infection than if it had been able to be collected immediately.

She urged me to consider public cord blood donation, which I had done and in fact was still open to. The hospital was a major centre for OzCord, the public donation people. She talked about it being easier to find a match if needed by a relative for leukaemia etc but I don&apos;t think she realised I was keen to collect my child&apos;s cord blood purely for their own use, which surely had to be a 100% match. I was collecting it for potential use if a stem cell cure for type 1 diabetes was found at some time in the future.

She also talked about the fact that giving the cord blood back to the child would only give it a &apos;double dose&apos; of its own genetics. She had a valid point, but with diabetes, sure the islet cells grown from the stem cells might peter out due to them being somehow diabetic islet cells and therefore the child go on to develop diabetes again, but if it took the amount of time it took for mine to peter out for instance, the child would still get 12 diabetes-free years out of their new islet cells! And perhaps there would still be enough cells left over for the next infusion. Or some other technology available to produce more when needed?

Anyhow, I certainly did have my own ethical dilemmas (guilt) about trying to save my own child&apos;s cord blood for some futuristic very slim chance cure when the child might never even develop diabetes (1 in 30 chance for each child). If another child or adult could use it now to actually cure their leukaemia for instance, it definitely felt selfish to hoard it. I wanted to find out exactly what the cure rate was with cord stem cell use in these diseases but the contact at the public donation centre was unable to help me with those statistics. 

Anyhow, as it turned out the public cord collections were closing down for two weeks at Christmas time, from 23rd December, so given that my due date was now 28th December, I could not donate the blood even if I wanted to.

This fact, plus my own relating of the reasons I sought to save the cord blood (ethical dilemma of having cord blood for one child but not the other, fact that diabetes could be such a devastating condition - end stage renal failure, cost to community etc), seemed to sway my obstetrician. She said she had no idea that the public collection people closed down over Christmas (I said it would be such a shame if no one could use the stem cells). She said she would work with me to collect the cord blood. Still, she did caution me that I would be their first priority and there was a chance it might not work. I think she also was a bit uncertain as she, herself, had not done a private collection on her own. Understandable.

When I mentioned the cord stem cell issue to my former ob, who had done the collection for my first child, she said it should be straightforward and she would have no hesitation with collecting it again for me as long as there were no complications at the birth. Could see no dramas. She actually had some private cord blood brochures on display in her waiting room and spoke about one doctor who was able to get an amazing amount of cord blood in his collections.

So obviously there is quite a wide range of attitudes out there amongst obstetricians with regard to private stem cell storage.

I still do feel uneasy about the ethics of private storage for a possible future when there are people who could use the stem cells now. However the public donation not being an option anyway due to them being closed over Christmas made my part of the decision-making with this pregnancy easy.

I wondered how many people did donate? How many did they need? As many as possible? I would ask any future friends if they were planning on donating as my guess is that few do.
      
   </content>
</entry>
<entry>
   <title>Stuffy nose rides again!</title>
   <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="./stuffy_nose_rides_again.html" />
   <id>tag:type1mum.net,2005://1.226</id>
   
   <published>2005-11-23T10:25:03Z</published>
   <updated>2007-04-15T02:51:38Z</updated>
   
   <summary>Just for the record, I think the nasal congestion that plagued me during my last pregnancy has just begun again. At 32 weeks. Only mild so far, but when I lie down I do seem to get a bit of...</summary>
   <author>
      <name>anon</name>
      
   </author>
         <category term="2nd Pregnancy" scheme="http://www.sixapart.com/ns/types#category" />
   
   
   <content type="html" xml:lang="en" xml:base="./">
      Just for the record, I think the nasal congestion that plagued me during my last pregnancy has just begun again. At 32 weeks. Only mild so far, but when I lie down I do seem to get a bit of a stuffy nose. 

Could this be the first sign of oedema? Didn&apos;t seem to be any in my feet yet, so hopefully it is a separate issue. 

I&apos;ve started using eucalyptus oil on a tissue under my pillow as it gives some relief. And I wouldn&apos;t mind buying a new bean bag to sleep on as it&apos;s the best thing I found last time when the nasal congestion got really bad.

Note - coming back and reading this post over a year later, I realise that I actually didn&apos;t go on to develop the nasal congestion of my first pregnancy after all. Thank goodness! It sounds minor when writing about it, but the inability to breath through my nose, particularly at night, during the last pregnancy, was massively distressing and contributed to my extreme, debilitating exhaustion at the end of my first pregnancy.
      
   </content>
</entry>
<entry>
   <title>Breastfeeding second time around</title>
   <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="./breastfeeding_second_time_arou.html" />
   <id>tag:type1mum.net,2005://1.227</id>
   
   <published>2005-11-23T10:29:13Z</published>
   <updated>2007-04-15T02:51:39Z</updated>
   
   <summary>I found breastfeeding my daughter very rewarding and such a lovely thing to be able to do after those first couple of days of separation while she was in the special care nursery. I had breastfed her for 19 months...</summary>
   <author>
      <name>anon</name>
      
   </author>
         <category term="2nd Pregnancy" scheme="http://www.sixapart.com/ns/types#category" />
   
   
   <content type="html" xml:lang="en" xml:base="./">
      I found breastfeeding my daughter very rewarding and such a lovely thing to be able to do after those first couple of days of separation while she was in the special care nursery. I had breastfed her for 19 months and was very keen to breastfeed this bub too. For as long as his little heart desired it.

MInd you,  I knew that having bub a bit early, being separated from him after the birth, and the possibility of me being unwell again, could interfere with breastfeeding. So I wanted to be as prepared as I could. Hoped to avoid the formula feeding that my daughter had been exposed to before the staff had even checked her blood sugar levels.

So off I went to see my trusty lactation consultant again. I had also booked in a breastfeeding (and attachment parenting) friendly paediatrician.
      
   </content>
</entry>
<entry>
   <title>No stuffy nose!</title>
   <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="./no_stuffy_nose.html" />
   <id>tag:type1mum.net,2005://1.228</id>
   
   <published>2005-12-02T22:00:42Z</published>
   <updated>2007-04-15T02:51:39Z</updated>
   
   <summary>I thought it had started again but apart from a mild case of stuffy nose some nights just as I lie down, I haven&apos;t (fingers crossed) encountered this problem so far in this pregnancy! 33 and a half weeks!...</summary>
   <author>
      <name>anon</name>
      
   </author>
         <category term="2nd Pregnancy" scheme="http://www.sixapart.com/ns/types#category" />
   
   
   <content type="html" xml:lang="en" xml:base="./">
      I thought it had started again but apart from a mild case of stuffy nose some nights just as I lie down, I haven&apos;t (fingers crossed) encountered this problem so far in this pregnancy! 33 and a half weeks!
      
   </content>
</entry>
<entry>
   <title>33 weeks - When to have the baby?</title>
   <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="./33_weeks_when_to_have_the_baby.html" />
   <id>tag:type1mum.net,2005://1.229</id>
   
   <published>2005-12-02T22:39:32Z</published>
   <updated>2007-04-15T02:51:39Z</updated>
   
   <summary>When to have the baby and whether or not to have steroids for a 37 week delivery to ensure the lungs are mature. I laugh when I read the subject title for this post as I realise that bub could...</summary>
   <author>
      <name>anon</name>
      
   </author>
         <category term="2nd Pregnancy" scheme="http://www.sixapart.com/ns/types#category" />
   
   
   <content type="html" xml:lang="en" xml:base="./">
      When to have the baby and whether or not to have steroids for a 37 week delivery to ensure the lungs are mature.

I laugh when I read the subject title for this post as I realise that bub could just decide to make his own early entrance and surprise everybody! But I just wanted to follow on from my previous 33 week post where I rave about whether or not to have bub right on 37 weeks or wait a bit longer....

According to my endocrinologist... &apos;They are just as good out as in at 37 weeks. Trying to wait until 38 weeks could be riskier for you and the baby. You are booked for the caesar mid-week (Wednesday) when there will be plenty of staff around (paediatrics etc). You don&apos;t want to be going into labour on New Year&apos;s Eve when there are fewer staff and people are pissed&apos;. (NB I think the last bit is a bit tongue in cheek but stilll...)

Endocrinologist on the topic of steroids... &apos;I wouldn&apos;t bother. Chances are they won&apos;t be necessary anyway (ie bub&apos;s lungs would be mature enough anyway) and it&apos;s a hassle for you (two extra days of hospitalisation) and will muck up your blood sugars. If we did do it the best way would be to admit you two days before the caesar, give you two courses of steroids and have you on an insulin/dextrose IV infusion and a sliding scale to keep tightest possible control of your blood sugar levels.
      
   </content>
</entry>
<entry>
   <title>35 weeks - still feeling good</title>
   <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="./35_weeks_still_feeling_good.html" />
   <id>tag:type1mum.net,2005://1.230</id>
   
   <published>2005-12-14T09:21:30Z</published>
   <updated>2007-04-15T02:51:39Z</updated>
   
   <summary>Well it&apos;s 36 degrees celsius here today and I&apos;m 35 weeks pregnant, but I feel positively spritely compared to how I felt at this stage with my last pregnancy. When I saw my docs last week my blood pressure was...</summary>
   <author>
      <name>anon</name>
      
   </author>
         <category term="2nd Pregnancy" scheme="http://www.sixapart.com/ns/types#category" />
   
   
   <content type="html" xml:lang="en" xml:base="./">
      Well it&apos;s 36 degrees celsius here today and I&apos;m 35 weeks pregnant, but I feel positively spritely compared to how I felt at this stage with my last pregnancy. 

When I saw my docs last week my blood pressure was still good (130/80) and there was only the mildest of oedema (no more than most women experience). I don&apos;t think this has changed but it will be interesting to see what happens at my doctors appointments tomorrow. Last week my protein had gone up to .96g per day, but this was still at least three times less than it was this time last pregnancy. I had put on a bit of weight (now up to 62kg) but this is only 10kg so far this pregnancy which is pretty good and doesn&apos;t necessarily indicate oedema. Yes, it will be interesting to see how I go tomorrow.

I do feel a bit guilty about my blood sugar control. My last HbA1C was 6.4. I&apos;ve had 6.3, 5.7, 5.9, 6.5, 6.1 and 6.4 this pregnancy. But last pregnancy I think I ranged from 4.9 to 6.3. So my sugars are a bit higher. Partly this is due to the hectic nature of looking after a toddler. But partly this is also due to me being quite preoccupied with getting things done. I suppose if I was only concentrating on my diabetes and the pregnancy it&apos;s possible I could have got even lower bsls. It would have been nice to have kept the Hba1Cs under 6.0 (non-diabetic range). My doctor tells me not to worry, it won&apos;t harm bub at this stage. The baby appears to be spot on normal size and doing well. Getting the control as tight as possible just before the delivery though will be a worthy goal, he says, as this will reduce the likelihood of my baby having hypoglycemia in the early days.

I had intended to start expressing breastmilk today but have been a bit lazy (busy) on that front. I hope I can collect some colostrum in advance though as it will help to keep bub&apos;s blood sugars up in the first couple of days, especially if I am unable to feed from the breast straight away.

NB It&apos;s common for babies of diabetic mothers to have low blood sugar straight after birth and important to keep their blood sugar levels normal to prevent any damage to the brain occuring. This can often be done via breastmilk feeds (colostrum) but sometimes it&apos;s necessary to give extra food (via expressed breastmilk, formula or intravenous glucose drip). After my first child was born, she was almost immediately fed formula. I was upset about this because I wanted to breastfeed and preferred her not to be given formula. This time I was determined that my child would not be fed cow&apos;s milk formula if at all possible. So was keen to take in a supply of my own expressed breast milk and to have some Neocate on hand (formula which contains only amino acids) to help keep my baby&apos;s blood sugar up if needed. I was also happy for the paediatrician to give my baby a glucose IV infustion if necessary. What I wanted most of all, was for my baby to be well enough and my medical team to be supportive enough, for me to be able to keep my baby with me rather than having him taken to special care.

In terms of steroids, I have decided not to have them unless my ob strongly encourages me to when I see her when she returns from overseas (five days before the booked caesar).  I&apos;ve decided this mostly because my endo, whom I trust more than anyone, really thinks it&apos;s unnecessary.

Other reasons are that I prefer to avoid a drug if I can, I don&apos;t like the idea of having to spend up to three extra days in hospital hooked up to a drip (for insulin, as steroids can cause a huge increase in insulin requirements), and the fact that if it was to be done it would have to be done in the days before bub&apos;s birth and I don&apos;t really trust &apos;the system&apos; to keep my blood sugars under control by drip (therefore risking hypos in the newborn). 

Quite frankly I also hate being &apos;at the mercy of nurses&apos; (although many of them are excellent), I also hate the thought of being away from my two year old daughter any longer than is necessary, and basically I think I&apos;d rather get other things done at that time than be admitted to hospital if possible. Having said all this, I would do it in a flash if I knew in advance my baby had a high chance of requiring days of oxygen after the birth due to immature lungs or retained fetal lung fluid.

Both my endo and my former ob (whom I&apos;m now seeing) seem to think I&apos;m much better having the baby at 37 weeks, when I&apos;ve been booked in, rather than trying to push it to 38. The fact that the two of them will be around that week and on leave when I am at 38 weeks is an important factor to consider.  But on the other hand I feel wierd too having my wee one extracted this early.

Perhaps I should just count myself lucky.
      
   </content>
</entry>
<entry>
   <title>headaches at 36 weeks</title>
   <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="./headaches_at_36_weeks.html" />
   <id>tag:type1mum.net,2005://1.231</id>
   
   <published>2005-12-19T01:05:42Z</published>
   <updated>2007-04-15T02:51:39Z</updated>
   
   <summary>Headaches this morning and last night. Crampiness and very frequent Braxton Hicks contractions for the past two days (but seems to have eased off now). My ob noticed a fair bit of uterine action in my CTG scan last Thursday,...</summary>
   <author>
      <name>anon</name>
      
   </author>
         <category term="2nd Pregnancy" scheme="http://www.sixapart.com/ns/types#category" />
   
   
   <content type="html" xml:lang="en" xml:base="./">
      Headaches this morning and last night. Crampiness and very frequent Braxton Hicks contractions for the past two days (but seems to have eased off now). My ob noticed a fair bit of uterine action in my CTG scan last Thursday, asked me if they were regular and said &apos;oh well if you go into labour this weekend we&apos;ll have a baby!&apos;

My old ob has been terrific and I feel very reassured and lucky to have her looking after me at this time. I appreciate her up front, honest, tell it like it is, manner this time around. She&apos;s been very supportive, helpful and understanding about my desire to collect cord blood for stem cells.

The thought of going into labour earlier than even the planned 37 week caesarean is something I truly have not given enough consideration to. I assumed my mum could drop everything and drive the one hour to be here and look after my daughter until my husband&apos;s parents arrived from interstate. But talking to her on the phone yesterday makes me think this is not to be the case. She works full time and I don&apos;t think would consider leaving work as an amergency if need be. This has thrown me into a panic.

I now have offers from a few friends to look after my daughter if I go into labour early which is lovely, but none so far are really great options for her. ie no one has offered to come here and stay at our house for say 24 hours, where she will feel more comfortable than at their house. And none of them have looked after her for an extended period of time. My friends are also about to go into labour themselves or else have one or two children of their own to look after, so asking for their help at this time is also pretty hard.

So far I still don&apos;t seem to have the oedema and my blood tests last week are still good, but &apos;drifting&apos;. I am due to get more today. See my ob tomorrow and have a growth scan on Thursday.

In addition to the two days of cramping (which I have assumed is probably just normal: baby pushing more against my cervix with a few more braxton hicks thrown in type thing) I am now really vague in the head. Spacey. Perhaps it&apos;s a bit panicky. It&apos;s hard to concentrate. Will get my blood pressure checked at the Chemist today just in case.

I have sent details of my daughter&apos;s routine to my mother in law, am depressed that so many of the things I really wanted to get done before bub 2 arrived are still not done, but there you go... and to be honest I feel guilty that I have not given enough consideration to the new baby. We still have no agreed upon name and I am waiting to get baby clothes sent up from my in laws. We sent ours down to my sister in law when she had her baby a year ago. So I&apos;m a bit stressed that bub doesn&apos;t even have much to wear yet.

Apart from that I guess everything&apos;s fine. I&apos;m off to finish packing my hospital bag....
      
   </content>
</entry>
<entry>
   <title>started expressing breast milk today!</title>
   <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="./started_expressing_breast_milk.html" />
   <id>tag:type1mum.net,2005://1.232</id>
   
   <published>2005-12-22T10:27:26Z</published>
   <updated>2007-04-15T02:51:39Z</updated>
   
   <summary>Yay! What a feeling of accomplishment it was today to find that I was able to express 4 ml of colostrum (early breast milk) for my baby! I am doing this so that if he needs a blood sugar boost...</summary>
   <author>
      <name>anon</name>
      
   </author>
         <category term="2nd Pregnancy" scheme="http://www.sixapart.com/ns/types#category" />
   
   
   <content type="html" xml:lang="en" xml:base="./">
      Yay! What a feeling of accomplishment it was today to find that I was able to express 4 ml of colostrum (early breast milk) for my baby! 

I am doing this so that if he needs a blood sugar boost or is unable to feed from the breast enough after the birth to keep his blood sugars up we will have a chance at feeding him breast milk rather than formula. I don&apos;t think formula is the worst thing in the world by any means, but given the fact that exposure to cow&apos;s milk protein or lack of breast milk _might_ increase bub&apos;s chances of developing type 1 diabetes, I&apos;d like to avoid the cow&apos;s milk formula if possible.

When my daughter was born she was fed formula straight away before her blood sugar levels had even been checked. I was shocked and disappointed as I had expressed my wish to breastfeed and avoid formula if possible. Apparently what happened with my daughter is not even standard practice. They only give formula if the baby&apos;s blood sugar level is low. 

Anyhow... I will probably have no more than 30ml of expressed breast milk stored for my baby by next Wednesday so they might still say he needs more. Or maybe by some miracle he will feed really well from the breast straight away and be brought to me for feeds regularly. Who knows.

It&apos;s tricky too. I don&apos;t want to sound radical with respect to the breast milk and bonding issue. My main concern is that the baby is doing well, breathing and everything else wise and I would never want to jeopardise his blood sugar levels. Being born just on 37 weeks there is a chance he will have retained fetal lung fluid and need oxygen for between 3 hours and 3 days. 

Being separated from your baby after the birth can be so traumatic. The staff last time were very good apart from the formula incident (paediatrician&apos;s decision) but feeling out of control and that your wishes are not being taken seriously and heard can be very upsetting.

Anyhow... once again... very excited to have got 4ml of colostrum this morning. Had intended to start collecting colostrum 2 weeks before the birth but have only gotten around to it now one week before.  At first I found no milk was coming out. Then only a drop or two. At one point the colostrum was dripping on to my hand but not into the little medicine measuring container I was using to collect the colostrum. I was about ready to give up in defeat when my lovely and well-seasoned husband came to my aid to help and encourage. I realised I needed to hold the container right up against my skin and that some milk was actually slowly trickling out. It gave me the confidence to continue and I&apos;m glad I did.

Today I tried to visit the special care nursery after my ultrsounds and CTG monitoring, but was told by the midwives at the ultrasound place that the special care staff were too busy to see me. In the end I went up just to peek in through the window. Just to get a feel for where my baby would probably spend its first day at least. I went to ask a receptionist where the nursery was and then just burst into tears. That was when the special care nurse came out and saw me. She was friendly and caring but I feel pretty soon in some way dismissed me. I can&apos;t put my finger on it, but as I now have to go and lie down (I&apos;ve been on my feet all day and my ankles are swollen) I will paste what I wrote about the experience to a friend of mine in an email.

Tomorrow at 1pm I&apos;m due to see my ob who has just arrived back from New York today. It&apos;s going to be an important appointment as we&apos;ll deciding whether or not to go ahead with the caesar at 37 weeks. Back to the email...

It&apos;s going to be interesting to see what happens with the expressed breast 
milk in my case. They give babies of diabetics about 20-30 ml per feed 
(eight feeds a day) of formula and I bet (unless my paediatrician tells them 
to do otherwise which I think he will) they  will say the colostrum we have 
collected is not enough and needs to be supplemented. In my understanding 
colostrum works completely differently so that it&apos;s actually some active 
components of the colostrum that cause gluconeogenesis (ie causes the baby&apos;s 
liver to make it&apos;s own sugar) so surely a much smaller amount is required to 
increase the baby&apos;s blood sugar?

I can&apos;t believe how difficult it was to just have a chat to a staff member 
in special care today. It was only the fact that I went up &apos;illegally&apos; that 
I was able to talk to someone. The midwife downstairs was just so rude to 
me, saying that they only organise tours for public patients and if my 
doctor thought it was important for me to visit special care they would have 
organised something for me etc etc etc. I tried explaining that all I wanted 
to do was see where my baby would probably spend at least the first 24 hours 
of his life (as I will likely be bed-bound for that period and unable to 
visit and will not have time prior to the caesar to meet, visit or talk with 
anyone) and that I also wanted to ask them how they would like me to supply 
the expressed breast milk to them to feed the baby. But I&apos;m sure all they 
saw was &apos;trouble-maker&apos;. Grrrr!! I don&apos;t want to scare you... the people up 
in special care are generally very lovely and perhaps they thought I wanted 
to deprive my baby of enough glucose for it&apos;s brain or something, but it 
never ceases to amaze me how hard it is to feel that you have rights or even 
valid input into your baby&apos;s care. I think the woman was even suspicious 
about the quality of the expressed breast milk we are freezing!!! grrr... 
sorry I&apos;m raving. I also had two very nice interactions. The woman who did 
my scan was my favourtie and complimented me on everything as usual (she always says how well I look and how well bub looks and tells me I&apos;m doing a great job with my diabetes) and the consultant who I asked to see was lovely too. Hope you are having a good day :-)
      
   </content>
</entry>
<entry>
   <title>Visit to my ob (just back from NY)</title>
   <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="./visit_to_my_ob_just_back_from.html" />
   <id>tag:type1mum.net,2005://1.233</id>
   
   <published>2005-12-23T09:15:33Z</published>
   <updated>2007-04-15T02:51:39Z</updated>
   
   <summary>I saw my ob today. Just back today after one month in New York. She thought I looked good (I was wearing my look good outfit and probably should have chosen something more middle of the range! No seriously, it...</summary>
   <author>
      <name>anon</name>
      
   </author>
         <category term="2nd Pregnancy" scheme="http://www.sixapart.com/ns/types#category" />
   
   
   <content type="html" xml:lang="en" xml:base="./">
      I saw my ob today. Just back today after one month in New York.

She thought I looked good (I was wearing my look good outfit and probably should have chosen something more middle of the range! No seriously, it makes a difference to the comments I get. One outfit and people say, wow are you having twins? and you look tired and the other outift and they say, wow you look great.)

Anyhow getting carried away.

Upshot:

Initially she started talking about moving the dates back a bit so bub could be older than just 37 weeks when born. Then by the end of the appointment, after seeing that my ankles were swollen with the beginnings of oedema and my blood test results were drifting onto the downward slope, she said her gut feeling was that next Wednesday was actually the right date to go with.

I have to get blood tests done tomorrow morning and she is going to talk with my endocrinologist and the paediatrician and then phone me to let me know the decision tomorrow afternoon (Christmas Eve). I suspect it will be all go for next Wednesday.

I felt some relief at being closer to a decision, but after speaking with the paediatrician on the phone this afternoon I felt anxious and a bit sad again. He mentioned that retained fetal lung fluid and even hyaline membrane disease could both be present in a baby born at 37 weeks, although it wasn&apos;t common.

The ob talked about being able to deliver the baby slowly even with a caesarean, letting it&apos;s head lie for a minute and giving the baby a bit of a squeeze as she pulled him out of me. Doing it gently and removing the placenta gently too. It sounded lovely to me. The squeezing helped with removal of lung fluid she said.

She also said I should be able to get up to see my baby the night after he is born being wheeled up, which was reassuring to hear. 

I can&apos;t overstate how wonderful it was to have my desire for the most natural birth possible (even though it was a caesarean!) taken into account. And to have my obstetrician so willing and eager to work with the lovely, breastfeeding-friendly paediatrician. She had suggested him to me herself when I told her I was exceptionally keen to breastfeed.

I also so appreciated the obstetrician I&apos;d been seeing while my ob was overseas telling her how important the cord blood collection was to me and giving a really detailed handover to her when she got back from overseas.

The paediatrician (at the appointment I had with him a couple of weeks ago) also spoke about the possibility of the baby being able to be with me on the ward if he was doing well. Wow. How different that would be. Still I fear for him being born early. I hope he will be alright and I really wish I had been able to be even better with my blood sugar control. The last HbA1Cs have been 6.4 and 6.5. Higher than I had with my daughter. Certainly not in the non-diabetic range. Hmmm. Fingers crossed.

I would have my expressed colostrum with me. Hopefully together with my expressed or fed straight from the breast milk this would be enough to keep his blood sugars up. Once again, fingers crossed. We will see.

Wow - We still haven&apos;t named him. And wow, still feels like so much left to do around the house. I think now it&apos;s list time. Write all the plans and ideas on a list so that at least they can be donw over the next year or so as time allows. 

Only four days to go...
      
   </content>
</entry>
<entry>
   <title>Steroids after all!</title>
   <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="./steroids_after_all.html" />
   <id>tag:type1mum.net,2005://1.234</id>
   
   <published>2005-12-25T08:35:27Z</published>
   <updated>2007-04-15T02:51:40Z</updated>
   
   <summary>Well, in an interesting twist of fate it looks like I&apos;m getting a dose of steroids after all to give bub&apos;s lungs an extra helping hand in case he needs it. Not sure how I feel about this. A bit...</summary>
   <author>
      <name>anon</name>
      
   </author>
         <category term="2nd Pregnancy" scheme="http://www.sixapart.com/ns/types#category" />
   
   
   <content type="html" xml:lang="en" xml:base="./">
      Well, in an interesting twist of fate it looks like I&apos;m getting a dose of steroids after all to give bub&apos;s lungs an extra helping hand in case he needs it.

Not sure how I feel about this. A bit relieved I guess as I was worried about having a baby who wasn&apos;t quite ready to come out and this should at least help the lungs. But I&apos;m pissed off that they are leaving it to the 11th hour to give me the steroids (just 36 hours before bub&apos;s birth) as it will almost certainly play havoc with my blood sugar levels and mean that bub will be born with a greater chance of hypoglycemia and that I will be hooked up to a drip for several days for insulin rather than being able to stay well-controlled on my pump. 

I would have preferred to have had the steroids a week before the birth to give my blood sugar levels a chance to restabilise. I mentioned this to my obstetrician a month ago before she went on leave and I mentioned it to my endocrinologist and the ob looking after me while the other one was away. No one seemed to agree with the idea of having me in hospital earlier. I think they think of the hassle factor ie this way there is just one hospital admission. But if we&apos;re really doing this to avoid bub having to spend unneccessary time in special care due to retained fetal lung fluid, shouldn&apos;t we also be doing what we can to avoid bub having to be in special care due to hypoglycemia?

When I talked with a diabetes educator who had been a great supporter of my pregnancy on the pump last time (when no one in my city had had experience with it) she agreed that giving the steroids a week before the birth would probably be a better option. But with my obstetrician overseas it was virtually impossible to organise this.

I&apos;m concerned about the effect of the steroids on my kidneys and my breast milk. I&apos;m concerned about extreme highs and lows which could be dangerous for me and the baby. I hope it will all be managed well, but it&apos;s still a bit nerve-wracking.

So there you go, I&apos;m heading off to hospital tomorrow night to get my first dose of steroids. I&apos;ll be remaining there until the birth a day and a half later, and then for up to a week after that.

Wish me luck...
      
   </content>
</entry>
<entry>
   <title>Beautiful Baby Boy!</title>
   <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="./beautiful_baby_boy.html" />
   <id>tag:type1mum.net,2006://1.235</id>
   
   <published>2006-09-17T01:14:50Z</published>
   <updated>2007-04-15T02:51:40Z</updated>
   
   <summary>I can&apos;t believe it has taken me this long to write my final entry... but there you go! Life with two little children is very busy!! My darling baby boy was born at 7.30am on 28th December, healthy and beautiful...</summary>
   <author>
      <name>anon</name>
      
   </author>
         <category term="2nd Pregnancy" scheme="http://www.sixapart.com/ns/types#category" />
   
   
   <content type="html" xml:lang="en" xml:base="./">
      I can&apos;t believe it has taken me this long to write my final entry... but there you go! Life with two little children is very busy!!

My darling baby boy was born at 7.30am on 28th December, healthy and beautiful with his long eyelashes and full head of gorgeous dark hair. Thanks to my wonderful paediatrician, as soon as he was seen to be healthy and breathing well, he was placed straight onto my chest for a profound, loving and relaxed cuddle. Skin to skin contact with my beautiful boy. He just lay there for the longest time, curled up and content. 

As soon as I got to recovery I put him to the breast and he nuzzled and fed beautifully straight away. We fed him a syringe worth of the breastmilk that I had expressed for him in the previous week and he drank that too. This was to give his blood sugars a boost.

As planned and suggested by my lovely obstetrician, my baby boy was taken gently out of me, his head lying on my tummy for awhile before he was totally born. So gentle.It was as natural a caesarean as I could have hoped for.

To my delight, I was able to bring him back to my room with me rather than having him whisked away to Special Care for a day and a half which was what had happened with my daughter. I tested his blood sugars while the nurses watched at regular intervals and was advised by my paediatrician to make sure he got 30ml ** of expressed breast milk with each feed (every three hours) after he had fed from the breast. This amount was calculated based on his weight and was to ensure that his blood sugars were kept up. He was an amazing drinker and drank quite massive quantities really for a newborn! 

The steroids I had been on for the day and a half before his birth had indeed caused my blood sugars to be higher than I would have liked at times and I am sure this was reflected in the fact that he suffered hypoglycemia on day one. Still, his hypos were not severe and in fact most of them may not even have been hypos but the normal lowish blood sugar of the newborn. Anyway, he was getting plenty of breast milk and his sugars stabilized.

I was determined to avoid him being fed formula if possible due to the question mark over whether early exposure to cow&apos;s milk protein might be a trigger for developing type one diabetes, so was pleased to be able to keep him topped up on expressed breast milk and milk direct from the breast. Mind you, this involved me expressing quite a lot at each feed when my own stores of expressed breast milk from the previous week ran out. I managed quite an incredible amount of colostrum for day one but at one feed I couldn&apos;t quite get enough, so my wonderful paediatrician appeared with some Neocate formula. It contains amino acids rather than the whole protein so is used for instance in highly allergic babies who need formula. We used this once or twice.

After his blood sugars had been stable for awhile I stopped the expressing and fed just from the breast. Interesting in hindsight how nerve wracking this was for me. I so wanted to make sure that his sugar was high enough and I couldn&apos;t see just how much he was getting from my breast. But going just to the breast was exactly what we both needed now and soon we were both confident.

How lovely to be breastfeeding again. To feel all that lovely Oxytocin flowing though me again. I was the happiest person on the face of the earth.
      
   </content>
</entry>
<entry>
   <title>Being on a drip.. grrr...</title>
   <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="./being_on_a_drip_grrr.html" />
   <id>tag:type1mum.net,2006://1.236</id>
   
   <published>2006-09-17T01:46:11Z</published>
   <updated>2007-06-09T14:28:12Z</updated>
   
   <summary>At the risk of casting a shadow on what was a truly beautiful event, it was quite horrible at times, being hooked up to the insulin dextrose drip for the two days before the birth, day of the birth and...</summary>
   <author>
      <name>anon</name>
      
   </author>
         <category term="2nd Pregnancy" scheme="http://www.sixapart.com/ns/types#category" />
   
   
   <content type="html" xml:lang="en" xml:base="./">
      At the risk of casting a shadow on what was a truly beautiful event, it was quite horrible at times, being hooked up to the insulin dextrose drip for the two days before the birth, day of the birth and morning after. 

The first issue was that the midwives could not find me a mobile drip. I knew in advance that I wanted to keep as mobile as possible before and after the birth. Partly because it helps you recover quicker, also because being immobile and having a caesarean (also probably having diabetes and kidney disease) increases your risk for developing DVT (Deep Vein Thrombosis) post birth.

Mobile drips (where you can walk around but take your drip with you) were available at the hospital, but it was difficult for the nurses to track one down for me. It took them a day, so I was immobile. I think people thought I was mad (when I finally did get the mobile drip) the night before the birth and the morning of the birth when they saw me wandering the hospital corridors attached to my drip. But I was determined to be as fit as possible. Even the one day lying mostly immobile had affected my body making me feel a bit stiff and weak!

The other thing that happened to me that seems to have faded into insignificance now but was actually scary and potentially  life-threatening at the time, was that I was given a massive dose of insulin via the mobile drip accidentally on the day my son was born. 

Partly the problem resulted from the fact that the midwives did not seem to know how to operate this drip. For the entire time I was on the drip (thirty six hours before the birth and at least a day after) an alarm would go off intermittently indicating that there was some error. Some midwives would try to sort it out themselves. Others would get another midwife with more expertise to come an help, while others would simply flick at it and seem to be pressing buttons almost randomly to make the drip stop beeping! It was totally disconcerting and resulted in me not getting much sleep at all the night before the birth.

But the scary incident happened on the day of the birth. The alarm went off to notify the midwives that my drip had run out of insulin. The midwife attached the new bag to the drip and entered the two required numbers into the drip machine. One was the amount of total insulin in the bag. The other was the hourly rate at which the insulin was to be infused. We did not realise it but she had gotten the two numbers wrong. Result: I was given a huge dose  of insulin in a short time. The machine would have gone on giving me this amount (something like 60 units an hour) only the machine beeped again, causing the midwives to come in yet again and realise what they had done. So they switched the figures and set the machine up properly.

The worst thing about this was that although they fixed the rate problem, it didn&apos;t dawn on them that they had just given me a massive dose of insulin. I started to have a hypo that felt like the bottom was dropping out of my universe and then my partner who luckily was there at the time, realised what had happened. I skulled a lot of lucozade and was eventually okay, but it was quite upsetting nonetheless.

My obstetrician apologised to me the next morning and said that she would make a recommendation to the hospital that a protocol would be set up for this machine that would require two nurses to be present whenever the drip was being set up or an alarm was being tended to.

It&apos;s so difficult in these situations, as the nursing staff are often under a lot of stress and time pressure due to staffing limits, but as my obstetrician said, had it been, for instance Morphine, that was in the drip, it could easily have been life-threatening.

The other foul thing about being on the drip was the sliding scale used to determine how much insulin I should be having. It was really hard to come to grips with this after so tightly controlling my own blood sugar levels for so long using the pump. 

My sugar levels did definitely increase due to the two steroid injections but perhaps not as much as my doctors thought they might. On quite a number of occasions I was told that I would be given an amount of insulin by infusion based on the sliding scale calculations that was way smaller than what I would have given myself on the pump for the meal I was about to eat. I knew my sugar levels would rise considerably after this and it was extremely stressful knowing that this would pass over to my baby and more than likely result in hypoglycemia in his early hours. On a few occasions I gave myself injections of fast acting insulin to lower the sugars that I knew would result from the sliding scale method. I was not meant to do this but felt compelled to in order to avoid massive highs passing through to my baby. I also avoided eating some of the sweeter foods. My doctor assured me that the insulin dose required would be so high and the sugars so hard to control that what I ate would not make an impact, but I disagreed.

I&apos;m not sure that I would have done anything differently. But it was difficult relinquishing control at this time and I think in retrospect I probably would have tried to keep my pump on and adjust my own levels during this pre birth steroid period (in conjunction with my doctor). I feel I might have had a chance at keeping my sugar levels better controlled than they were.
      
   </content>
</entry>
<entry>
   <title>Over one year later</title>
   <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="./over_one_year_later.html" />
   <id>tag:type1mum.net,2007://1.237</id>
   
   <published>2007-02-17T05:46:22Z</published>
   <updated>2007-06-09T12:04:42Z</updated>
   
   <summary>Wow - Once again I can&apos;t believe it&apos;s taken me so long to get back to this diary to finiah it off. Life is busy with a beautiful fourteen month old boy and an energetic, imaginative and inspiring three year...</summary>
   <author>
      <name>anon</name>
      
   </author>
         <category term="2nd Pregnancy" scheme="http://www.sixapart.com/ns/types#category" />
   
   
   <content type="html" xml:lang="en" xml:base="./">
      Wow - Once again I can&apos;t believe it&apos;s taken me so long to get back to this diary to finiah it off. Life is busy with a beautiful fourteen month old boy and an energetic, imaginative and inspiring three year old girl to look after. It&apos;s exhausting at times, but life is also indescribably gorgeous. I feel incredibly lucky to have my two precious little ones in my life and very grateful to my medical team, my friends and most importantly my wonderful life partner for their support during my two pregnancies and beyond.

At my endocrinology appointment a couple of weeks ago I found out that my kidneys had recovered from the second pregnancy. The protein was 0.26, pretty much the same as it had been just prior to conceiving my son and even better than it had been prior to conceiving my daughter! So my kidneys have seemingly bounced back. Great news.

Sometimes I feel as though I have three children. The third is my diabetes.  I&apos;m always needing to check... just what is this third child up to now? It&apos;s a wily child, an unruly child, and often it gets neglected in the busy immediacy of having to look after my two real children.

My most recent HbA1C was 8.9 which is not great at all. Partly it&apos;s because I tend to eat late these days and fall asleep before being able to check that my blood sugar is settled for the night. Often my sugar levels are quite high on waking. My baby boy sleeps near me. When I wake to feed him at night the last thing I feel like doing is turning on the light to test my blood sugar. But that&apos;s what I need to do to get my blood sugars down again. That and to record my bsls. That is what has always helped. But it does take some disciplne. Also I know I tend to under-insulinise because I dislike having hypos. Hmmm.

I&apos;ve had a couple of dreams lately about having an actual third child, but have no logical intention of doing so. I&apos;m thirty-nine for a start. Perhaps this third child actually is my diabetes? I owe it to my children to get my diabetes under control again so that I can be around for them and healthy for them for as long as possible.
      
   </content>
</entry>

</feed>
